<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>writing on ssaraf</title>
    <link>https://ssaraf.com/tags/writing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in writing on ssaraf</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ssaraf.com/tags/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Crypto in the cave</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/crypto_in_the_cave/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/crypto_in_the_cave/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Crypto seems to be a great divider amongst my friends and colleagues. Some think of it as the next step in human innovation, the future of finance, a political and social movement, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others, including myself, see it as a horrible mixture of Ponzi scheme, MLM campaign, and suicide cult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a technical perspective, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to provide much utility over existing solutions - no software engineer chooses a ledger over, say, a database. You will have a hard time finding a company &amp;ldquo;built on crypto&amp;rdquo; that is not in some way also selling crypto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a financial perspective, it seems to be a way of avoiding well-justified regulation (and is thus a great place to take old financial tactics like wash trading and re-use them on a new generation of fools). Since bitcoin and its ilk don&amp;rsquo;t represent economic activity like stocks / bonds, it seems that its only intrinsic value is to sell it to someone who thinks they can sell it for more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My minimal economics experience makes me skeptical of deflationary currencies. Some folks compare investing in crypto to investing in gold. But I think investing in gold is stupid too - it only makes sense as a hedge against other trades. Crypto is correlated with the market, but more volatile, so would make a bad hedge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only thing crypto seems to do well is enrich a small group of people who created whatever token / NFT thing is popular, and a larger group of VCs and tech companies &amp;ldquo;selling shovels&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, gold, like stocks and everything else at the moment, trades far above intrinsic value. Why not have a meme token that trades for more than the market caps of half the S&amp;amp;P?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, while I think crypto is stupid, I could be wrong. My point isn&amp;rsquo;t about crypto specifically, but about why my friends disagree about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People I know used to segment the way you&amp;rsquo;d expect if you were a political reporter in the early 2000s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s the city dwelling, tech / finance / law / medicine working, IPA-drinking, educated crowd. They invite people to dinner parties with multiple appetizers. They only vaguely care about sports. They vote for Democrats until they get rich, after which they become libertarian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there&amp;rsquo;s the &amp;ldquo;flyover country&amp;rdquo; dwelling, blue collar job working, gun wielding, street smart crowd. They have kids early. They have barbeques and watch football. They vote for Republicans as a rule but only vaguely care about politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more thoughts on these two groups, see this piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doesn&amp;rsquo;t the above seem incredibly old fashioned? The first is now a &amp;ldquo;woke mob&amp;rdquo; who will very carefully eat &amp;ldquo;organic&amp;rdquo; food and have strong opinions about gender identification on your Zoom username, and the second proudly wears MAGA hats but not face masks and has strong opinions about post-op trans women using female bathrooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this was just about political polarization, that would be one thing. But now the reality distortion field of the most recent elections seem to have rubbed off on everything that we discuss. Crypto is the latest example of many in which the questions are insane, and up is down, and black is white. Conversations about almost anything are nerve-wracking - even writing the above makes me worry about either being cancelled or summoning some type of red-hat mob.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the worst thing is that, generally speaking, I don&amp;rsquo;t care about most of it. I agree that much of it is important to other people. But not to me, except in the vague sense of wanting to talk about something other than the weather - these subjects come up most often in conversation. I feel guilty about not caring enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For topics that I do care about, I see a streak of subjective, anecdotal, vague thinking which is worrisome, since it seems to be coming from all angles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, my left-leaning friends are all vaccinated, but most (if not all) will eat at restaurants indoors that have a &amp;ldquo;mask on&amp;rdquo; policy. Aerosolized viruses transmit just fine while you&amp;rsquo;re eating - putting the mask on while talking but taking it off to eat food is stupid. If you&amp;rsquo;re going to take the mask off to eat, keep it off. Or eat outdoors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the current administration&amp;rsquo;s tactics around school closures, giving vaccines to children, etc have erred irrationally conservative. This leads parents to do well-justified things like smuggle their 11 and 4 year old kids to get the vaccine earlier than they &amp;ldquo;should&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the right, there&amp;rsquo;s almost too many examples to name. Perhaps the proud anti-vax and anti-mask groups are the easiest to pick on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m reminded of the allegory of the cave. We&amp;rsquo;re all seeing shadows on the wall, and nobody knows what&amp;rsquo;s real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you wanted to find out the truth about crypto, where would you go? Who would you ask? If you wanted to find the truth about vaccine effectiveness, where would you read it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the problem is that no one knows. There is no authority that can be trusted to give accurate, practical answers to these questions. The CDC, for example, will give accurate but not risk-adjusted recommendations. For example, early on in the pandemic, they were wrong about the utility of masks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some prominent folks will give closer to optimal recommendations, but their voices are diluted along with all the other loud people, and the reason they have a voice is, forgive me, they&amp;rsquo;re good at Twitter, or appearing on talk shows. Do we really think that the best authority on any subject is the one that emerges from the cauldron there? Or are we just picking the top dog in a mangy pack? For every Zeynep there is a Joe Rogan, and we can&amp;rsquo;t ignore that they emerged in the last few years in roughly the same way. How do we know which is which?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn&amp;rsquo;t enough to &amp;ldquo;study the science&amp;rdquo; either. You can read here about a detailed meta-analysis done by Scott Alexander on ivermectin, with the conclusion that it &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; help patients with COVID, so long as they&amp;rsquo;re in a country where the populace has worms and therefore a dewormer helps improve clinical outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point isn&amp;rsquo;t Scott&amp;rsquo;s specific conclusion but the type of analysis that&amp;rsquo;s needed to interpret even a &lt;strong&gt;meta analysis&lt;/strong&gt; of scientific studies on a subject of immense practical value to all of humanity for the last two years. No one could possibly have the time to do the &amp;ldquo;from first principles&amp;rdquo; analytical approach in every area, so you have to read some one else&amp;rsquo;s summary, and right there you&amp;rsquo;re depending on that person&amp;rsquo;s credibility and platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before now, credibility and platform were determined by a small group of elite institutions, on both the left and right. It didn&amp;rsquo;t matter if you were conservative or liberal, the WSJ and NYT would &lt;em&gt;retract incorrect pieces&lt;/em&gt; if they were found to be misleading in even the smallest way. Scientific studies were published in prominent journals, and you would suffer professional consequences if you put something inaccurate in a paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who succeeded at those institutions were academically or professionally qualified, so you could trust what you read. And while those organizations still exist and are present in today&amp;rsquo;s discourse, it feels like they&amp;rsquo;re drowned out from the mass of loud voices on more &amp;ldquo;decentralized&amp;rdquo; platforms like Twitter, Substack, Youtube, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one issues a &amp;ldquo;retraction&amp;rdquo; on Twitter, unless the mob comes after them. And even in those circumstances, the person recanting isn&amp;rsquo;t doing so because of what&amp;rsquo;s factually accurate, but because they need the mob - it&amp;rsquo;s their platform, after all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so rather than accuracy or truth we go for who can say the most interesting things, or the funniest jokes, or who can build an audience, which are different sorts of skill sets. You can&amp;rsquo;t even find the humble truth-seekers because these platforms only throw popular people at you to follow, not those poor shmucks tweeting to &amp;lt;100 friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;rsquo;s in that world where people are making new digital currencies and the mob is buying them up and they go up in value and more people join the mob to get in on the action, and soon you have an NFT of a picture of Elon Musk worth more money than can even be conceived of, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t do anything except reflect its own ever-increasing demand and fixed supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crypto can go to the moon, for all I care. I wish those people well. But I want a place to read about it that will put facts above whatever religion they&amp;rsquo;ve adopted. I worry that I have my own blind spots - things that I believe that aren&amp;rsquo;t really true, but I&amp;rsquo;m in a weird self-reinforcing bubble that makes me believe them stronger and stronger. And I&amp;rsquo;m not sure where to go.&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a personal brand</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/building_a_personal_brand/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/building_a_personal_brand/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;One logistical update - I&amp;rsquo;ve centralized the posts that would usually go to the sudopoint or SQL blog to this one. If you were subscribed to sudopoint or on my SQL class mailing list, you&amp;rsquo;re now subscribed here.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m surprised to see many of my friends starting to build public online presences. Previously they didn&amp;rsquo;t seem to want to. Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the reason seems to be that many of them are starting companies, and CEOs often have to do a lot of marketing. Without a pre-existing marketing machine, they try to bootstrap one from their personal social accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think it&amp;rsquo;s more than that, and I think there&amp;rsquo;s a link to some of the earlier thoughts on this blog related to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssaraf.com/keynesian_workweek&#34;&gt;work week&lt;/a&gt;, and building &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssaraf.com/side_projects&#34;&gt;side projects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We are each our own little company now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That converts &amp;ldquo;full time employment&amp;rdquo; into something that looks a lot more like one larger company subcontracting work to a smaller company (You Inc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also explains why employers increasingly are looking to reduce global benefits in favor of those that the individual employee can decide how to wrangle. Instead of insurance benefits, pay enough salary that employees can buy on the exchange. Instead of dumbbells in the office, a stipend for doing whatever workouts you want. Instead of 8 hours a day each day, spend however much time you need to get the job done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also explains why &lt;em&gt;getting&lt;/em&gt; a job is such a weird experience. Almost no one who gets a job gets it by applying for it via a website. Instead it&amp;rsquo;s about relationships you&amp;rsquo;ve built - effectively, how well you can market yourself as the best subcontractor for the position. Sure, the company doesn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;call you&lt;/em&gt; a contractor, but you can end the contract tomorrow and go start another one, just like a contractor can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gig economy workers already knew about all of this, of course. But this emerging independence has usually been painted as primarily an advantage to employers, who get away with providing fewer perks to a captive employment base. I think the opposite - this is an advantage, though largely unexploited, for employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, there&amp;rsquo;s a large &lt;a href=&#34;https://overemployed.com/&#34;&gt;community of people&lt;/a&gt; that now work two &amp;ldquo;full time&amp;rdquo; jobs. For those of us just working the one, we know that it&amp;rsquo;s perfectly possible (in fact, likely) that you only get 10 or 20 hours of productive work in for an employer per week. For highly circumscribed roles, with concrete independent deliverables (i.e. non management), getting multiple jobs is a brilliant approach to maximize your income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, successful companies are getting smaller. And not just startups - I mean regular companies can be built &amp;ldquo;off the shelf&amp;rdquo; and so simply require fewer personnel to get a product to market. The rise of the Indie Hacker movement has been astronomical, and I think will only continue to swell. Journalists are leaving newspapers to start substacks, where they can earn money directly, on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect that the maximally employable people will be those that take advantage of this structure to market themselves effectively. The main problem is that most of the people I know doing this are, bluntly, super boring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I occasonally peruse twitter, and even the &amp;ldquo;intelligent tech&amp;rdquo; people are primarily posting what I would consider to be absolute drivel. Epigrams that would drive Confucius crazy. Statements that seem controversial but are really just paper thin assessments of the obvious. They are effectively text-only rorschach images meant to get forwarded around as simply the next version of chain letters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of these posters are pretty thoughtful people, many of whom are brilliant writers. But they need to use twitter / linkedin / facebook as sort of a marketing mechanism to catch a little bit of attention from the vast sea of internet fish. Which they then funnel into whatever scheme they&amp;rsquo;re peddling - youtube channels, substack subscriptions, try my startup, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog isn&amp;rsquo;t an exception, but I can at least be honest about that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More importantly, I think it has implications for those of you reading who don&amp;rsquo;t already have an online presence. All signs point to you being at a disadvantage compared to those who have shamelessly sleazed themselves out on social media. Probably not in your current role, but certainly when looking for a new one, or starting a project that requires a global audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, the people who I most respect in my past workplaces, who are often the wisest, most thoughtful people, they often have no meaningful online persona. They don&amp;rsquo;t link to tweets. They barely watch youtube. As far as I can tell, many of them don&amp;rsquo;t even have linkedin profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That makes me think that as loud and obnoxious as the current online discourse is, the vast majority of people in real life are not writing online at all, and most (especially the most talented and experienced) are barely reading it. They know it&amp;rsquo;s mostly crap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it is still early in the game. I wonder if participating in it will actually be an advantage, or instead an indicator of which people clumsily jumped into a fad that will eventually fade.&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>