<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>philosophy on ssaraf</title>
    <link>https://ssaraf.com/tags/philosophy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in philosophy on ssaraf</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssaraf.com/tags/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The power of names</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/2019/power_of_names/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/2019/power_of_names/</guid>
      <description>The power of names is really interesting to me. Sometimes it seems like concepts that previously were muddled become much more simple to understand once you give it a unique set of phonemes that others can reference.
I&amp;rsquo;ll give an example from work recently. A few weeks ago I was given an assignment that was rather broad in scope. It was unclear (and is still unclear, as of this writing) exactly what the eventual product will look like.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Minimize the distance from idea to execution</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/2018/idea_to_execution/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/2018/idea_to_execution/</guid>
      <description>My company is getting more and more &amp;lsquo;political&amp;rsquo;. If you wanted to do something new, you used to have to spend weeks getting the proper permissions / sign offs from the relevant leadership, ensure they were bought in to the vision of your project, talk to the resourcing team to make sure you had the critical materials and personnel, talk to legal to ensure they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t block you later, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Problems and solutions</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/2018/problems_and_solutions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/2018/problems_and_solutions/</guid>
      <description>Something I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed recently is that problems become a lot easier to solve if you describe them in detail. That is, attempting to solve a vague, multi-faceted issue is practically impossible, but cutting it down to a set of discrete problems seems to make it much more digestible. Part of this is, no doubt, that we make things more tangible, but I think there&amp;rsquo;s more to it that that.
Why is it, for instance, that the solved problems in a particular field of study are well known, but it&amp;rsquo;s not obvious what the unsolved problems are?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get bored</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/2018/get_bored/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/2018/get_bored/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking and talking about side projects for a long time. Now is the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve shipped something that 1) actually works and 2) has at least a snowball&amp;rsquo;s chance of becoming something people use.
Why is that? I now get bored.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t used to. It always felt like there was an infinite number of things to read on the internet and an infinite number of TV shows to watch.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Momentum equals habit</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/2018/momentum_equals_habit/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/2018/momentum_equals_habit/</guid>
      <description>Novices to finance are always amazed at how powerful compound interest is. Once they become aware, it becomes much easier to explain why they should pay off high interest loans as quickly as possible, and not keep too much cash lying around that isn&amp;rsquo;t gathering interest.
But people are always slow / hesitant to apply the same knowledge to other aspects of their lives. Regular, steady contributions (even mediocre ones) will outgrow and crush the sprinters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Holding it all in your head</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/2018/holding_in_your_head/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/2018/holding_in_your_head/</guid>
      <description>Something I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed when working on larger programming projects is that my ability to add new code depends on what stage of the project I&amp;rsquo;m at. Early on, the code comes out fast. However, as time goes on and the project gets bigger, I find that it takes me up to an hour to &amp;ldquo;load the program into my head&amp;rdquo; before I can begin to add new features.
Good code is read most often by the writer, not by the computer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Be tangible</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/2018/be_tangible/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/2018/be_tangible/</guid>
      <description>Something that I see again and again is mistaking imprecision for wisdom. For instance, if I asked you: &amp;ldquo;go out and get 10 more users&amp;rdquo;, that&amp;rsquo;s a tangible, easy to understand goal. If I tell you, &amp;ldquo;we need to increase penetration of our software&amp;rdquo;, then you have to add a translation step to try interpret the meaning of what I&amp;rsquo;m saying (do I mean add more users or add more time per user?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human knowledge</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/2018/human_knowledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/2018/human_knowledge/</guid>
      <description>It took Newton the better part of 3 years to &amp;lsquo;invent&amp;rsquo; calculus. [1] He is considered to be one of the brightest mathematical minds to have ever lived. Yet most 17 year olds today are capable of mastering the same calculus he did. Why is that?
It&amp;rsquo;s almost too obvious to say - it&amp;rsquo;s easier to learn something than it is to imagine it. More interestingly, there seems to be a kind of inflation with learning.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
