<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>philosophy on ssaraf</title>
    <link>https://ssaraf.com/tags/philosophy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in philosophy on ssaraf</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ssaraf.com/tags/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The power of names</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/power_of_names/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/power_of_names/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The power of names is really interesting to me. Sometimes it seems like concepts that previously were muddled become much more simple to understand once you give it a unique set of phonemes that others can reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll give an example from work recently. A few weeks ago I was given an assignment that was rather broad in scope. It was unclear (and is still unclear, as of this writing) exactly what the eventual product will look like. But we needed some kind of framing to help us grapple with the complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to make something up. I roughly bucketed the 4 types of workflows that I thought we would want to support, and I named each one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened next somewhat surprised me. Not only was my method of categorizing rapidly spreading around the organization, but the paradigm with which I used to make them spread too. It was like I had performed inception on an entire organization, just by giving something a unique name and definition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of other things now begin to lock into place. For instance, why do medical conditions seem to be fractally deep? It feels like there are new &amp;ldquo;types of types of &amp;quot; cancer every year. Not because more people are diagnosed, but because by attaching a name to a specific set of data, we can grapple with it more easily and, hopefully, find patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about religion or philosophy? There&amp;rsquo;s nothing more common than an academic philosopher taking a perfectly ordinary concept and trying to name it. Even the name &amp;ldquo;God&amp;rdquo; itself is just a bucket of ideas which are not only difficult to express, but some argue can only be felt or sensed, rather than measured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a way, a name is merely a pointer to an idea in the same way that pointers can tie to arbitrarily large and complex objects in computer systems. But why use a name? The same reason you would want to use a pointer. It&amp;rsquo;s easier and cheaper to pass it around, and everyone can immediately understand what it means just by dereferencing. Names as a new form of primitive can be combined and understood much more deeply, at least by our limited human minds.&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Minimize the distance from idea to execution</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/idea_to_execution/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/idea_to_execution/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My company is getting more and more &amp;lsquo;political&amp;rsquo;. If you wanted to do something new, you used to have to spend weeks getting the proper permissions / sign offs from the relevant leadership, ensure they were bought in to the vision of your project, talk to the resourcing team to make sure you had the critical materials and personnel, talk to legal to ensure they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t block you later, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays that process takes &lt;em&gt;months&lt;/em&gt;. Based on conversations with friends at  larger companies, the process is even longer there. That&amp;rsquo;s not necessarily a bad thing - by forcing so much consensus the company tends to build things in line with the existing business objectives. And because those business objectives fluctuate rapidly (at least from an executive&amp;rsquo;s perspective) the company size usually scales with how &amp;ldquo;top-down&amp;rdquo; the decision making becomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s been interesting is observing how the increase in delay has changed the ability of the team on the ground to be effective. The more the organization tries to influence a team, the slower it seems to go. Why is that? What actually takes up their time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My argument would be that a lot gets &lt;em&gt;lost in translation&lt;/em&gt;. That is, when the project lead describes what is being worked on to leadership, the leaders don&amp;rsquo;t actually have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssaraf.com/be-tangible.html&#34;&gt;tangible understanding&lt;/a&gt; of what&amp;rsquo;s happening. But they think they do. And so rather than one unified perspective on what the product should look like, there are several competing perspectives. The project lead him or herself can&amp;rsquo;t distinguish between which vision is right, and so he / she ends up building a melded version of several visions at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In most cases, I would argue that the project lead would be better off ignoring the leadership (politely) and just building the v0 or a set of mocks that accurately represents the current plan. When developing a product it&amp;rsquo;s hard to &lt;em&gt;describe&lt;/em&gt; what the thing should do and much easier to just &lt;em&gt;show what it does&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One example came up in work a couple weeks ago. I had described a mechanism to accomplish something that everyone wanted done, but my descriptions were not specific enough for the team leads to understand what I was saying &lt;em&gt;to a degree they could act on it&lt;/em&gt;. When I finally made a simple example and sent it to them, I could almost hear the &amp;ldquo;oh, &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; is what you meant!&amp;rdquo; go off in their heads. And weeks of back and forth ended almost immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s another aspect to this which I want to explore more. It&amp;rsquo;s almost as if a promising idea is a pure, concentrated thing at first. It&amp;rsquo;s exciting to go after, one is confident it&amp;rsquo;ll be successful, its scope is small, etc. As more people contribute to the idea to feels like it gets diluted somehow. Not that the contributions are bad, per se, but by adding on so many appendages it becomes this huge monster that&amp;rsquo;s much harder to execute on. In that sense, doubling the functionality (before the initial version exists) usually quadruples the amount of development time. That would explain what happens when the functionality demands continue to rise - velocity of the engineering team asymptotically approaches zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea that good contributions to a project idea could end up killing it is a counterintuitive one. It reminds me of Warren Buffett&amp;rsquo;s way of prioritizing tasks&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Write down a list of your top 25 priorities in the next year in order of most important to least important. Circle the first 5. The other 20 now become your &lt;em&gt;avoid at all costs&lt;/em&gt; list.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Problems and solutions</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/problems_and_solutions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/problems_and_solutions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Something I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed recently is that problems become a lot easier to solve if you describe them in detail. That is, attempting to solve a vague, multi-faceted issue is practically impossible, but cutting it down to a set of discrete problems seems to make it much more digestible. Part of this is, no doubt, that we make things more &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssaraf.com/be-tangible.html&#34;&gt;tangible&lt;/a&gt;, but I think there&amp;rsquo;s more to it that that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is it, for instance, that the solved problems in a particular field of study are well known, but it&amp;rsquo;s not obvious what the unsolved problems are? My understanding is that even talented scientists have to &amp;ldquo;load into their head&amp;rdquo; the full landscape of known work in order to figure out where the gaps are. If they tried to describe ALL the gaps, they&amp;rsquo;d never stop - the number of problems that could be worked on is infinite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while that is strictly true, I still think more could be done there. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty clear that, for example, theoretical physicists don&amp;rsquo;t have a ton of variance in what they work on. If we asked one to describe &amp;ldquo;what are the interesting unsolved problems in your field &lt;em&gt;that people are working on&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; the list wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be that long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it seems that between the illumination of our existing knowledge and the darkness of the unknown there is a silver lining where humanity is bustling, trying to spread a little further beyond. Seemingly the only way to know where that silver lining is&amp;hellip;is to go to graduate school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part of me wishes that comprehensive, detailed descriptions of the unsolved problems in a given field were published in the same way that our solutions currently are.&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;rsquo;s not obvious to me how possible this is, but the current attempts are quite crude [1] and I think by enumerating the problems clearly, we&amp;rsquo;d be able to surmise solutions more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Dev. &amp;ldquo;Unsolved problems in biology - The state of current thinking&amp;rdquo; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0079610715000115&#34;&gt;Progress in Biophysics and Molecular Biology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get bored</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/get_bored/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/get_bored/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking and talking about side projects for a long time. Now is the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve shipped something that 1) actually works and 2) has at least a snowball&amp;rsquo;s chance of becoming something people use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is that? I now get bored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t used to. It always felt like there was an infinite number of things to read on the internet and an infinite number of TV shows to watch. Of course, I would mostly reread the same websites and rewatch the same shows. Not hard for a journey to be infinite if you go in a loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My work was also&amp;hellip;intense. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t at all unusual to work 12 hour days, in a country where I knew almost no one, return to the paid-for corporate apartment, eat some food on the company card, go to the gym wearing a company shirt, and go to sleep, repeat. Nowadays I almost always finish work at 6 PM, so I have a lot more free time than before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what made me decide to break out of the loop. But I began treating it as an addiction. I considered myself to have absolutely no ability to enjoy such things in moderation, and that the only path was to teetotal my way to freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I found myself to have lots of time. Hours and days that used to fly by suddenly went terribly slowly. Have you ever spent a day without internet, or TV, and nothing to occupy your time? I worked out, played my guitar, called friends on the phone, wrote, and programmed [1]. Once I&amp;rsquo;d been doing this for a few weeks, it became a &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssaraf.com/momentum-equals-habit.html&#34;&gt;habit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if I had to provide some advice on how to be productive in something that isn&amp;rsquo;t your day job, that&amp;rsquo;d be my recommendation. Don&amp;rsquo;t bother trying to get &amp;ldquo;motivated&amp;rdquo;, or to find some secret pseudo-scientific trick that&amp;rsquo;ll make you more productive. In fact, you can start now. Close this browser window, sit in a chair, and stare at the wall for 15 minutes. If you&amp;rsquo;re anything like I was, you won&amp;rsquo;t be able to do it without checking your phone within a few minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect that screen addiction will be seen as smoking was in the previous generation. If you were to ask a former smoker why they smoked, they would say &amp;ldquo;it&amp;rsquo;s just what everyone was doing&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;we did it to pass the time&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;we did it to socialize with other people&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;it was fun&amp;rdquo;. All things you could say about the internet today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What scares me a little bit is how complete the conspiracy seems to go. I can think of hardly anyone who doesn&amp;rsquo;t spend the vast majority of their free time watching tv or reading the internet. Even people who enjoy the outdoors, or play music, or cook, or are getting ready to have kids. It all seems to be in service of, ultimately, an arrangement of pixels on a screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Programming seems like an unusual thing to be proud of doing, given my rant about screen addiction. I don&amp;rsquo;t consider &lt;em&gt;reading or watching&lt;/em&gt; to be the same thing as &lt;em&gt;writing or creating&lt;/em&gt;. To me, the latter is much, much harder.&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Momentum equals habit</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/momentum_equals_habit/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/momentum_equals_habit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Novices to finance are always amazed at how powerful compound interest is. Once they become aware, it becomes much easier to explain why they should pay off high interest loans as quickly as possible, and not keep too much cash lying around that isn&amp;rsquo;t gathering interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But people are always slow / hesitant to apply the same knowledge to other aspects of their lives. Regular, steady contributions (even mediocre ones) will outgrow and crush the sprinters. The tortoise always beats the hare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first started going to the gym it was a huge struggle. I set myself a goal, which perhaps could help you too - go to the gym, even if it&amp;rsquo;s only for 15 minutes, and even if you just play pool in the lounge and read your phone, &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; day. What you&amp;rsquo;ll find, as I did, is that after a few days of this you&amp;rsquo;ll say to yourself &amp;ldquo;well maybe I can do just one exercise, maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll play some basketball&amp;rdquo;. A week later, you might start fiddling around on one of the machines. A week later, free weights. You&amp;rsquo;ll get fitter and fitter, and if you look at the amount of exercise, either by intensity or by length of workout, it&amp;rsquo;ll start to look exponential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, of course, it&amp;rsquo;ll level off. None of us are super saiyans. What really happens is that your initial discipline will rapidly get you to a new minimum fitness level which you can maintain or increase over time, and now going to the gym is habitual, rather than motivation based. The curve looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;%7Bfilename%7D/images/motivation_habit.png&#34; alt=&#34;S curve&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This curve happens everywhere in biology - and biologists talk about things that &amp;ldquo;shift the curve left&amp;rdquo; (which speeds up the exponential phase) or &amp;ldquo;shift the curve right&amp;rdquo; (which makes it longer). Your effort, on the other hand, looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;%7Bfilename%7D/images/effort.png&#34; alt=&#34;Negative saturation curve&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second curve isn&amp;rsquo;t a surprise either - for instance, the first curve can represent hemoglobin - oxygen binding, and the second curve represents how much oxygen is present in substrate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think this is an accident. When we descibe &amp;ldquo;habit&amp;rdquo; we&amp;rsquo;re only describing the mental infrastructure that guides our actions as humans. You wake up in the morning, and if you eat breakfast every day, you begin to reinforce neural pathways that are involved in that: your hypothalamus and stomach secretes hormones related to digestion and hunger, your brain pushes the parasympathetic nervous pathways that allow you to digest the food, etc. If you don&amp;rsquo;t eat breakfast, those pathways begin to wither - or more precisely, activating them is on the exponential part of the S curve: you have to force yourself to eat, because you aren&amp;rsquo;t hungry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We probably already know this subliminally - if you play video games every day, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t take an extraordinary amount of effort to play them today. But if you never play them, you&amp;rsquo;ll rarely want to, even if you could. The more sugar you eat, the more you crave sugar. Regular wine drinkers find cracking the next bottle easier. Etc. Same with chess or exercise or programming or&amp;hellip;writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no immediate solution if you can&amp;rsquo;t get yourself to do the first 15 minutes, though. Certainly I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted to start a blog for &lt;em&gt;years&lt;/em&gt;, and never executed, and many of the side projects I&amp;rsquo;m pursuing now are ideas that have been bouncing around my head since my old college days. No time like the present, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one thing I will say, which is reinforced in the math, is that the first day is always the hardest, and then the second day is the second hardest&amp;hellip;until the curve flips. When it does, you&amp;rsquo;ll find it&amp;rsquo;s actually harder &lt;em&gt;not to do&lt;/em&gt; the thing than it is to do it - your neurons don&amp;rsquo;t seem to distinguish between action and inaction. That means starting bad habits is just as hard as ending them. That knowledge is comforting, somehow.&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Holding it all in your head</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/holding_in_your_head/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/holding_in_your_head/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Something I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed when working on larger programming projects is that my ability to add new code depends on what stage of the project I&amp;rsquo;m at. Early on, the code comes out fast. However, as time goes on and the project gets bigger, I find that it takes me up to an hour to &amp;ldquo;load the program into my head&amp;rdquo; before I can begin to add new features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good code is read most often by the writer, not by the computer. So if you keep your codebase concise and simple, you win twice: 1) it takes less time to read and understand and 2) it&amp;rsquo;s easier to modify. Perhaps that&amp;rsquo;s why experienced software engineers advise you to &lt;em&gt;pick a boring stack&lt;/em&gt;, particularly for projects you&amp;rsquo;re starting on your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly for me, the excitement of a new language or library often drives my initial interest in a project. It turns out this is stupid. Very soon afterward, I find myself blocked in an ever continual parade of stack overflow posts and difficult to comprehend bugs. For a while I thought I was &lt;em&gt;learning&lt;/em&gt; by going through this process. I usually wasn&amp;rsquo;t, because the new library did something I already knew how to do, just in a more fashionable way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does this principle apply to anything else? Yes, it does - it applies to pretty much all of my creative endeavors, including writing. If I try to write in a sophisticated, &amp;ldquo;wise&amp;rdquo; way, I find that it takes me a lot longer to load the dialogue into my head, improve it, and finalize it. The only reason this blog is beginning to gain momentum now is because I gave up on trying to write that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the scary thing. My writing is not just easier, it&amp;rsquo;s better than it was before. By using my natural voice and not coming off so stilted, I can approach topics and think more deeply through problems; I no longer have to think in a foreign language, so my focus is on the topic at hand rather than the words I&amp;rsquo;m using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, if you&amp;rsquo;ve been tracking the projects I&amp;rsquo;m working on, you should expect the number of interesting libraries I use to go &lt;strong&gt;down&lt;/strong&gt;. Sorry, the goal for me is a piece of software that accomplishes a goal, not source code that adheres most to the fashion of the day. And you can expect that I&amp;rsquo;ll be more productive as a consequence.&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Be tangible</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/be_tangible/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/be_tangible/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Something that I see again and again is mistaking imprecision for wisdom. For instance, if I asked you: &amp;ldquo;go out and get 10 more users&amp;rdquo;, that&amp;rsquo;s a tangible, easy to understand goal. If I tell you, &amp;ldquo;we need to increase penetration of our software&amp;rdquo;, then you have to add a translation step to try interpret the meaning of what I&amp;rsquo;m saying (do I mean add more users or add more time &lt;em&gt;per&lt;/em&gt; user?). If I tell you, &amp;ldquo;our mission is to take over the world&amp;rdquo;, you would be very justified is asking what the hell I was talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get it - we have ideas in our minds and sometimes words can only capture the overall sense of what we&amp;rsquo;re trying to communicate, not the specifics. Language cannot perfectly convey ideas. And big thinkers, like the CEOs and leaders we all hope to become someday, tend to have so much experience (or think they do) that they shrink from describing a specific instance, and instead try to extract whatever fundamental idea they believe sums it up. These phrases are almost always universal truths that no one can deny but have no useful, actionable meaning. &lt;em&gt;Life is short&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Be kind&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be evil&lt;/em&gt;. Etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re trying to communicate something specifically, &lt;strong&gt;say it&lt;/strong&gt;. I think we underestimate how many of our words are lost in translation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My brain -&amp;gt; my words -&amp;gt; your ears -&amp;gt; your brain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to make this journey as easy as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, because leaders tend to speak in generalities, people who want to become leaders speak the same way - except worse. They don&amp;rsquo;t have the background to know how to abstract meaning from experience. And good speakers can intercalate their general propositions (&amp;ldquo;healthcare is a right!&amp;rdquo;) with specific examples (&amp;ldquo;Jim had prostate cancer, and wasn&amp;rsquo;t insured, so he couldn&amp;rsquo;t get his medication in time to prevent his death&amp;rdquo;). Novices don&amp;rsquo;t have the anecdotes; the generalities are just shallow truth-speak and there&amp;rsquo;s nothing deeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what you end up with is a terrible word salad - a bunch of conceptual mumbo jumbo that no one, including the speaker, actually understands. The only thing I grasp from such moments is: 1) this person probably doesn&amp;rsquo;t know what they&amp;rsquo;re talking about, and 2) they want to look like they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite examples of this is from Richard Feynman, who describes reading a paper by a sociologist afflicted with the same syndrome:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I stopped at random and read the next sentence very carefully. I can&amp;rsquo;t remember it precisely, but it was very close to this: &amp;ldquo;The individual member of the social community often receives his information via visual, symbolic channels.&amp;rdquo; I went back and forth over it, and translated. You know what it means? &amp;ldquo;People read.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see smaller forms of this pretty much everywhere. People will have a bickering, long discussion about, ultimately, the definition of a sophisticated sounding word. Sometimes they&amp;rsquo;ll even invent the word! There&amp;rsquo;s nothing like a neologism to make you sound clever. And because it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been defined yet, you get to bend the language to the actions you want to take, rather than the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My solution to this is to always add a translation step whenever I think someone is being unclear, and repeat it back to them. Here&amp;rsquo;s an example of a typical dialogue:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Them: We want to build a structured mechanism by which users can ingest their own data into the existing infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Me: Gotcha, so you want to create a form that can add rows to this dataset.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Them: Not only that, but we also want to productize the workflow so that other people can easily compound on it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Me: Ok, agreed, we need to make the form easy to use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you see, I keep a specific example, ideally of what we plan to do in the short term, constantly in discussion. If we&amp;rsquo;re begin to veer off and talk about what this will look like in the next 6-9 months, I stop the conversation, politely. I don&amp;rsquo;t mind planning, but most people are terrible at planning and really good at playing out vague fantasy escapades. It would be one thing if the fantasy escapades had even a 50% likelihood of coming to pass. They never do. People who have the diligence to plan out a new project a year in advance don&amp;rsquo;t have the foresight to realize how much will change after the first 2 months. Planning is less and less useful the farther out you project, and at some point your variance in outcomes is beyond what can be feasibly predicted. No plan survives the first battle, as they say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I&amp;rsquo;ve found is, conveniently, once I&amp;rsquo;ve translated from vague nonsense to understandable language, people can begin to engage and provide feedback. They poke and prod and iterate. In other words, we can actually build the thing. Victory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Feynman, &amp;ldquo;Surely You&amp;rsquo;re Joking Mr. Feynman!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human knowledge</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/human_knowledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/human_knowledge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It took Newton the better part of 3 years to &amp;lsquo;invent&amp;rsquo; calculus. [1] He is considered to be one of the brightest mathematical minds to have ever lived. Yet most 17 year olds today are capable of mastering the same calculus he did. Why is that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s almost too obvious to say - it&amp;rsquo;s easier to learn something than it is to imagine it. More interestingly, there seems to be a kind of inflation with learning. The best high school students today might learn calculus at 15, rather than 17. And &amp;lsquo;best&amp;rsquo; in this instance actually seems to describe the school, rather than the student. It&amp;rsquo;s been well established that school quality is a far better predictor of academic success than anything else. [2]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&amp;rsquo;s not about how much horsepower your brain has. If subjects are taught to you in the right way, you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to master more difficult concepts than your parents did, at a younger age - both because of this inflation effect and because more will have been discovered by the time you get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anecdotally, there always seem to be folks who learn things far younger than others in their generation. For them, the general quality that sets them apart seems to be their precociousness, not their intelligence. Younger students often lack the discipline to focus for more advanced coursework. Once they gain the grit and work ethic of adults, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to stop them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus it&amp;rsquo;s always been a big frustration to me when people say &amp;ldquo;I just can&amp;rsquo;t do math&amp;rdquo;. Barring a diagnosable mental deficiency, this is never true. Most often students struggle not because the material is difficult but because they lack the discipline to keep working at it or are thinking about it from the wrong perspective. It is alarming how often it is the latter - kids work a lot harder than we give them credit for. But teachers are often abysmally bad at teaching them the right paradigms, often because they never learned them correctly in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common case I see of an incorrect paradigm is the student who leans on memorization to get through exams. Studies pretty clearly demonstrate that even with clever tricks like spaced repetition or mnemonics, long term recall for everyone is abysmally low. Relying on it to pass your test sounds good in the short term, but really it seems that you cut off the learning that other parts of your brain could be getting, like your reasoning skills. Perhaps that&amp;rsquo;s why absent minded professors have such bad memories. They don&amp;rsquo;t happen to have bad memories despite being able to reason well. They reason well &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; they have bad memories. They didn&amp;rsquo;t have the crutch to lean on, so their muscles grew stronger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some careers, like law or medicine, are so old fashioned they continue to teach as if memorizing lengthy material is necessary, even though practicing physicians and lawyers don&amp;rsquo;t remember the details from their licensing exams only a few years before. The paradigm they are really learning in medical school is a sense of what is &amp;ldquo;weirder than usual&amp;rdquo; and what isn&amp;rsquo;t. For symptoms that they don&amp;rsquo;t immediately recognize, they google it, like anyone else would. [3]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That isn&amp;rsquo;t to say that paradigms are everything. There will always be some basic facts and theories that need to be learned by rote in any field. One also may have to hone specific technical skills. But nonetheless it appears that every subject has some kind of limiting reagent - a few concepts that, once students really grok, make the rest of the field feel like a simple extension of what one already knows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The broader question is whether one can pick up new paradigms even beyond the young age at which most of them are initially acquired. I would argue that yes you can, so long as you already have the paradigm of paradigms - that ultimately the person who created the knowledge was not a young person. Newton was capable of inventing calculus at an older age. So you must be capable of at least understanding it now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t think you&amp;rsquo;re as smart as Newton was? Surely you&amp;rsquo;re not as dumb as an average 17 year old. Sandwiched between the two, there is virtually no concept across any subject of human knowledge that you are incapable of understanding. And your children will pick it up faster than you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average length of a PhD is about 7 years. [4] Even that is an overestimate of the knowledge one needs to acquire, since the majority of that time is spent trying to cobble together something to contribute to the field. That means the entire body of human knowledge, visualized as a swimming pool, is only 7 years deep. The average human lifespan is &amp;gt;78 years. [5]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only reason you aren&amp;rsquo;t an expert at something new is because you haven&amp;rsquo;t had the discipline and the paradigms needed to get there. I&amp;rsquo;m not offering a solution to this. But I do expect that within my lifetime, the vast human potential for knowledge acquisition and usage will not stay as untapped as it currently is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thanks&lt;/strong&gt; to Otis Reid and Karthik Prasad for reading drafts and providing feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] The conflict between Newton and Leibniz is quite famous. But Fermat and other mathematicians discussed the principles of calculus long before both of them. In fact, Newton&amp;rsquo;s work is considered to be a new paradigm (along with a mathematical framework) on top of Fermat&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;theory of tangents&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/261805&#34;&gt;Card, &amp;ldquo;Does School Quality Matter&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] Good physicians don&amp;rsquo;t use wikipedia, but UptoDate and AccessMedicine are the medical equivalents, with proper citations. That said, you&amp;rsquo;d be frightened by how often wikipedia &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[4] The length of the average PhD appears to be decreasing in the past few years, which was quite surprising to me. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nsf.gov/statistics/2018/nsf18304/datatables/tab31.htm&#34;&gt;National Science Foundation, National Center for Science and Engineering Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[5] &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/gerontologist/article/55/6/901/2605490&#34;&gt;Crimmons, &amp;ldquo;Lifespan and Healthspan: Past, Present, and Promise&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>