<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Op-ed on ssaraf</title>
    <link>https://ssaraf.com/categories/op-ed/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Op-ed on ssaraf</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ssaraf.com/categories/op-ed/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Cheapness</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/cheap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/cheap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a famous stat around Google search. Apparently for every 100 milliseconds the developers shaved off of search times, the number of searches went up several fold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this phenomenon is everywhere, and is deeply underestimated. Particularly if you start with the assumption that cost is a combination of money, time, and effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Econ 101: the lower the cost of something, the more demand you have. If you can cheapen something enough, it has an overhelming effect&amp;hellip;a lot more than I would have expected!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if you make beef cheaper at the grocery store, you see more people buying it (and fewer people buying chicken). If you make beef more expensive, people will buy less. But what&amp;rsquo;s the true cost of using the beef? The true cost is not just the money you spend buying it, but the time you spend cooking and preparing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which explains the popularity of McDonald&amp;rsquo;s. Fast food provides beef really cheaply (both in terms of money and in terms of time) and therefore get lots and lots of demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a set of technological innovations that allowed fast food chains to come into existence - the microwave, the deep fryer on a timer, frozen potato fries that could be made repeatably and consistently, large scale distribution, franchises, etc. But once those innovations were in place, it became almost too easy to make food, and therefore very cheap to eat it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obesity is a bigger problem (in the first world) than food scarcity because those innovations make it too easy to meet your caloric needs. For thousands of years humans were fighting to put enough food on the table, and now we fight not to put too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s lots of examples of cheapness causing outsized behavior in its favor. The cheapness is often created by an improvement in technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that while technology makes things cheaper, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily make them better. It sometimes makes things worse, by meeting a surface level need but making the overall experience more shallow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are some other examples of this phenomenon?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;public-transit&#34;&gt;Public transit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Manhattan it is easier to go north or south than east or west because of how the subway system is arranged. If you measure the distribution of where and how New Yorkers spend time, it looks like an oval around where they live or where they work, with the long axis of the oval pointing north / south. The same phenomenon happens for SF residents of the Mission. In cases where public transit isn&amp;rsquo;t easy enough, the distribution is circular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;social-media&#34;&gt;Social media&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media makes it easier to do a bunch of things, and therefore gets outsized attention in proportion to its value. For example it&amp;rsquo;s easier to tweet than write essays, so tweeting seems way more popular than blogs. Watching gifs is cheaper than videos, so gifs get more popular. Messages lose nuance and become shorter, faster, and meme&amp;rsquo;d.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This probably applies to communication in general. The friends I previously called on the phone now prefer to text. Colleagues prefer slack to email, to their detriment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;free-vs-non-free&#34;&gt;Free vs non free&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free donuts at the office or free samples at Costco or free ebooks online all seem to incentivize tons of people to participate. Many now popular things started as free experiences for users which then juiced their popularity, after which they started charging money for them. One example of this is Andy Weir&amp;rsquo;s book The Martian, which was written serially, for free, on his website, and only after it reached popularity did it go through the normal publishing process and start to make money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;home-gym-vs-membership&#34;&gt;Home gym vs membership&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inertia to travel to the gym is its main cost (at steady state), and it seems to have an overwhelming influence on how often you go. Crappy home gyms are often used an order of magnitude more than fancy gym equipment 10 minutes away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, walking to work is &amp;ldquo;cheap&amp;rdquo; compared to working from home and then proactively choosing to go on a walk (in this case, the price you pay is whatever motivational energy you have).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;organizational-incentives&#34;&gt;Organizational incentives&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you make it cheap to schedule a meeting (making calendars transparent, for example) then the organization, whatever its other goals, will have a lot of meetings. If you make it cheap to merge PRs, then more projects will get shipped to customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the above is usually only realized after organizations do the wrong things, i.e. keeping process and red tape cheap to add, but which makes getting products out the door expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;snacks-in-view-vs-out-of-sight&#34;&gt;Snacks in view vs out of sight&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is cheaper to eat something on the kitchen table than find a different food buried in the pantry. Putting unhealthy foods in physically hard to reach places or out of sight means you don&amp;rsquo;t eat them, and is a demonstrated way of eating healthier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;contact-us-vs-self-serve-pricing&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Contact us&amp;rdquo; vs &amp;ldquo;self-serve&amp;rdquo; pricing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customers will find the cost of manually reaching out to a sales rep to be so annoying and frustrating that they will hardly ever do it, and so will go with a competitor who has transparent pricing and a billing flow that doesn&amp;rsquo;t require talking to a person first (even if that competitor is worse). Companies hoping to price discriminate for each customer sometimes find themselves with fewer customers, none of whom are inbound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This same effect can be seen with sign up flows. Forcing a user to register for your web application before using it will often mean you get an order of magnitude fewer users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reading-list-like-articles-vs-reading-structured-prose&#34;&gt;Reading list-like articles vs reading structured prose&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lists require less cognitive cost, so we would expect a priori for this post to be more popular than most of the other ones on this site. We would expect buzzfeed articles to have higher readership than the typical New Yorker piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not obvious to me what the lessons of this should be. One lesson might be to &amp;ldquo;reduce barriers to entry&amp;rdquo;, which is all well and good, but sometimes those barriers to entry allow for a better and more deep experience. I don&amp;rsquo;t think I would recommend eating only fast food, or only texting friends rather than speaking to them on the phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, I think the power of cheapness in all its forms is a useful mechanism for understanding what groups of people are likely to do, whether it&amp;rsquo;s in their interests or not.&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Keynesian Workweek</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/keynesian_workweek/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/keynesian_workweek/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;pawn-shops&#34;&gt;Pawn shops&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say you want to buy a trinket from a pawn shop and sell it to someone else. In most cases, you aren&amp;rsquo;t going to be able to find a price equal to what you paid. The &amp;ldquo;spread&amp;rdquo; on your trinket is the difference between what you can sell it for (say, $10) and what you can buy it for (say, $20).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pawn shop owner, Jimmie, knows exactly how much the trinket&amp;rsquo;s worth - 15 bucks. Note that the value of the trinket is &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; somewhere between the bid ($20) and the ask ($10). This bid-ask spread is a measure of the &lt;em&gt;liquidity&lt;/em&gt; of the market, essentially the &amp;ldquo;price you must pay to &amp;ldquo;liquify&amp;rdquo; an otherwise illiquid asset.&amp;rdquo; [1]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;tick&amp;rdquo; in our pawn shop example is probably 25 cents. In your negotiation, you can probably offer $19.75 instead of $20 for your trinket. But you probably &lt;em&gt;can&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; bid $19.99 instead of $20. The one cent isn&amp;rsquo;t worth it, and he&amp;rsquo;ll smack you if you ask again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the &amp;ldquo;tick size&amp;rdquo; means that you might be overpaying for your trinket. The value of the trinket might actually &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; $19.90, but you have to pay $20 for it anyway. Practically speaking you can see this happening when an unfortunate soul doesn&amp;rsquo;t have enough money to quite meet the bill, and throws a bunch of pennies on the table in the hope that it gets &amp;ldquo;close enough&amp;rdquo; to be less than a tick away from the actual value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matt Levine has a great take on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2020-01-15/it-s-not-insider-trading-if-the-president-does-it&#34;&gt;tick size&lt;/a&gt;, if you want to read more. In the finance world, it&amp;rsquo;s interesting to note that by making the tick size smaller, &lt;em&gt;the market becomes more efficient&lt;/em&gt;. Yeah, read that again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, if Jimmie&amp;rsquo;s willing to round to the nearest dime instead of quarter, the spread on your trinket can shrink. That&amp;rsquo;s good news for both sellers to Jimmie (who get a higher price), and buyers from Jimmie (who get a lower price). But Jimmie, who gets stuck on the wrong side in either deal, misses his boat payment. You can be sure that pawn shop owners won&amp;rsquo;t negotiate to the penny anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other thing - the size of the tick depends on which market you&amp;rsquo;re in. Equities have a certain tick size, bonds have a different one, and so on. But as we&amp;rsquo;ve seen, financial markets aren&amp;rsquo;t the only place this applies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;legal-billing&#34;&gt;Legal billing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s talk about lawyers. Lawyers sell a service, rather than a physical good, but the way they bill for their time has a lot of similarities to our pawn shop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most lawyers bill at an hourly rate, and they &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; have a tick size - some lawyers bill to the nearest quarter of an hour, but most bill to the nearest &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cand.uscourts.gov/about/court-programs/criminal-justice-act-cja/cja-compensation-rates/billing-increment-chart-minutes-to-tenths-of-an-hour/&#34;&gt;tenth of an hour&lt;/a&gt;. A lawyer that bills $250 / hour therefore has a &amp;ldquo;tick size&amp;rdquo; of $25.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of things to note:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is that you can&amp;rsquo;t simply hire a lawyer for a single tenth of an hour. Most attorneys have some fixed amount of stuff that you need to purchase from them before they bill you this way - i.e. buy 10 hours worth of my time, then I bill in increments afterwards. Pawn shops have a similar setup - there&amp;rsquo;s a minimum price for everything in the store, and you can be sure it&amp;rsquo;s not a quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is that there is a cost associated with billing at smaller increments. Namely, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;way more annoying&lt;/em&gt; to track your time every 6 minutes. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t worth Jimmie&amp;rsquo;s time to bicker over pennies, but it actually costs lawyers time to track their hours, and that &lt;a href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2015/01/workers-are-bad-at-filling-out-timesheets-and-it-costs-billions-a-day&#34;&gt;cost sets a lower limit&lt;/a&gt; on what the tick size can be. Finance doesn&amp;rsquo;t really have this problem&amp;hellip;the tick size is whatever the exchange says it is, and it can be lowered (or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/a16bb892-6ee1-11e2-9ded-00144feab49a&#34;&gt;raised&lt;/a&gt;) relatively easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-functions&#34;&gt;Step functions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately that means that any time you sell something, the price to value function is not a continuous one, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Step_function&#34;&gt;stepwise&lt;/a&gt;. That is, you to have to sell some discrete additional value before the price goes up, and the price can only go up in increments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But most of you aren&amp;rsquo;t lawyers, and probably very few of you have gone to a pawn shop recently. Who cares?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually the service I sell most often is time to my full time employer. And that service is stepwise &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt;. In fact, to a first approximation, there are only two ways that I can sell my time to most employers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working as a fulltime employee, 40 hours a week, 48 weeks a year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not working as a fulltime employee, 0 hours a week, 0 weeks a year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standard of 5 days a week &amp;amp; 8 hours a day is totally arbitrary, apparently negotiated by labor unions &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fair_Labor_Standards_Act_of_1938&#34;&gt;80 years ago&lt;/a&gt;. But that&amp;rsquo;s the market. And due to the nature of this market, I can pretty much only sell (1) to &lt;em&gt;at most&lt;/em&gt; one employer at a given time, and have to put all other employers in the (2) category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now all those inefficiencies about tick size aren&amp;rsquo;t just some intellectual horsepuckey, it&amp;rsquo;s now how I make my living, and the tick size is &lt;em&gt;a mile wide&lt;/em&gt;, and no one&amp;rsquo;s talking about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;keynes&#34;&gt;Keynes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.econ.yale.edu/smith/econ116a/keynes1.pdf&#34;&gt;Keynes hypothesized&lt;/a&gt; that by now, people would be working 15 hours a week, because the average worker productivity would continue to go up, and people&amp;rsquo;s needs would long have been met with just that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus  for  the  first  time  since  his  creation  man  will  be  faced  with  his  real,  his  permanent  problem-how  to  use  his  freedom  from  pressing  economic  cares,  how to occupy the leisure, which science and compound interest will have won for him, to live wisely and agreeably and well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For  many  ages  to  come  the  old  Adam  will  be  so  strong  in  us  that  everybody  will need to do some work if he is to be contented. We shall do more things for ourselves than is usual with the rich to-day, only too glad to have small duties and tasks and routines. But beyond this, we shall endeavour to spread the bread thin  on  the  butter-to  make  what  work  there  is  still  to  be  done  to  be  as  widely  shared  as  possible.  Three-hour  shifts  or  a  fifteen-hour  week  may  put  off  the  problem for a great while. For three hours a day is quite enough to satisfy the old Adam in most of us!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s within sight right now! Many of the people I know in tech are making &lt;a href=&#34;https://danluu.com/bimodal-compensation/&#34;&gt;more money&lt;/a&gt; than they need. Some have turned to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jefftk.com/giving&#34;&gt;donating altruistically&lt;/a&gt;, others are obsessed with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mrmoneymustache.com/2018/10/05/the-fire-movement/&#34;&gt;retiring early&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I like having a regular job. There&amp;rsquo;s something satisfying about chipping away at an important problem, and I like being paid for it. But I would prefer to scale my work time in accordance with my needs. As in, I should be able to work for 3 days a week, and get paid 60% as much. Or in lieu of a 20% raise, I simply don&amp;rsquo;t work on Fridays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I can&amp;rsquo;t do that! Instead, I need to have a tough negotiation with my employer about salary where my needs are met with less than they are already paying me, but other employers pay more, so &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; need to pay me more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Employers are effectively paying me in both &lt;em&gt;time&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;money&lt;/em&gt;. Almost everybody in tech gets 2 days a week off, some salary &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt;, and some equity &lt;strong&gt;Y&lt;/strong&gt;. I simply want to convert the constant &amp;ldquo;2 days&amp;rdquo; into a variable which can be adjusted like the others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;unlimited-vacation&#34;&gt;Unlimited vacation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some tech companies have a policy called &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/the-rime-of-the-digital-mariner/the-myth-of-the-unlimited-vacation-policy-7fbdb5f02770#.hxed4covd&#34;&gt;unlimited vacation&lt;/a&gt;, the idea being that you can take as much time off as you want, and everyone will be happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m surprised nobody calls this out for the outright lie that it usually is. With a couple of notable exceptions, I can&amp;rsquo;t think of a single person who has successfully pivoted their unlimited vacation policy to working 4 days a week. Since that converts to about 1.5 months of vacation, it&amp;rsquo;s clear there&amp;rsquo;s some kind of cap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These vacation policies were only put into place after someone did the math and realized that the average employee will not take the standard amount of PTO. That&amp;rsquo;s especially the case if you force them to ask for it by the day, and have them face the social pressure of the rest of the team &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; taking that much time off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;contractors&#34;&gt;Contractors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know what you&amp;rsquo;re thinking - Sanjay forgot to talk about contractors. No, I didn&amp;rsquo;t. Being a contractor is great because you can in fact set your price and your time commitment to be anywhere you want, including within the tick size of being a full time employee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that contractors, by definition, can provide end-to-end value completely by themselves. And I can&amp;rsquo;t, at least not &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssaraf.com/p/0e274bab-9315-4158-ab02-416f57f36078/sudopoint.com&#34;&gt;yet&lt;/a&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s why an Uber driver can be a contractor - all they need is a functioning vehicle and an iPhone and they can provide discrete value. But the value I can provide is much closer to the cog that gets lots of other cogs to run faster / more efficiently. I&amp;rsquo;m valuable within a system, not an end to end system on my own. I suspect that most white collar employees are in the same situation as me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while it&amp;rsquo;s very possible for product managers or developers to work as contractors, you hit the same problem that you hit in any other illiquid market - there&amp;rsquo;s not a *ton *of buyers, so you tend to rely on the same few folks every time you sell your services, which means you may not be getting market value for your service. Sometimes, if you&amp;rsquo;re really good at selling, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.expatsoftware.com/articles/guy-on-the-beach-with-a-laptop.html&#34;&gt;this can be to your advantage&lt;/a&gt;. Other times, it won&amp;rsquo;t be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s nothing special about a 40 hour work week. We even have some evidence that workers are not as productive &lt;a href=&#34;https://psycnet.apa.org/record/1975-08475-001&#34;&gt;working 5 days as 4 days&lt;/a&gt; (though in that case, it was the same number of hours). There could be a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laffer_curve&#34;&gt;Laffer curve&lt;/a&gt; like effect on efficiency, and companies today may be on the far right side of the curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[1] Thanks to Andrew H for this excellent explanation and broader feedback on drafts of this article!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a software product on 5 hours a week</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/5_hours_a_week/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/5_hours_a_week/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I know that many folks out there (including you, don&amp;rsquo;t lie) are dreamers. You want a creation that not just makes a difference, but is yours. You could make something, put out your shingle, and let people pay you money for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us will fail in that ambition. Certainly I have so far. But now that I&amp;rsquo;ve managed to build a complete product I thought I&amp;rsquo;d capture some of the lessons I learned along the way. This is probably most useful for &amp;ldquo;bootstrapped&amp;rdquo; tech startups, not big companies or lemonade stands or coffee shops, but who am I to stop the friendly reader?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;are-you-a-developer-if-not-become-one&#34;&gt;Are you a developer? If not, become one.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of people, particularly those that went to business school (sorry, I can&amp;rsquo;t help but poke fun), think that creating a software business is as simple as writing down a good idea and merely getting an engineer to build it. Hint: there&amp;rsquo;s a reason that the number of successful software businesses started with Upwork contractors is approximately zero. If cash could reliably be turned into good software then you could put the venture capitalists out of business. Just sit in your room and meditate on ideas, then spend &lt;a href=&#34;https://danluu.com/bimodal-compensation/&#34;&gt;cash&lt;/a&gt; to hire software engineers to build them. How could you lose?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead it&amp;rsquo;s more common for the engineers to have the ideas, start to build them, then come to the VCs so they can grow faster. Instead of coming up with the ideas, the non-technical folks usually help manage existing products or offshoots, not build new ones from scratch. There are exceptions of course, but the successful entrepreneurs tend to look a lot more like &amp;ldquo;engineers who have business ability&amp;rdquo; than &amp;ldquo;business people who hired engineers&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is that? I suspect that while many folks can build a solution to an arbitrary problem, they vary quite widely in their ability to define the problem well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;know-your-stuff---create-a-circle-of-competence&#34;&gt;Know your stuff - create a circle of competence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building a product in software is an exercise in knowing where to deep dive and where to be satisfied with reasonable defaults. The types of decisions you make on the fundamentals (what language &amp;amp; framework, do users need to be logged in to try it, etc) actually end up changing the user experience dramatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say you aren&amp;rsquo;t an engineer. The problem isn&amp;rsquo;t that you aren&amp;rsquo;t smart enough (you probably are - this stuff isn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; complicated) but instead that you don&amp;rsquo;t even understand the paradigm by which you&amp;rsquo;ll be making decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s like trying to bake a cake without going into the kitchen. You can&amp;rsquo;t ask for &lt;a href=&#34;https://sallysbakingaddiction.com/vertical-cake/&#34;&gt;vertical lines&lt;/a&gt; instead of horizontal ones, without profoundly changing how the whole thing is built!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you might expect, one &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circle_of_competence&#34;&gt;circle of competence&lt;/a&gt; for a company building software is the &lt;em&gt;building software&lt;/em&gt; part. The market pays for outsize value - something a lot of these no-code based companies don&amp;rsquo;t realize. Yes, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of lego blocks out there which you can assemble together, but the real value you&amp;rsquo;re selling is the glue between those blocks. And since the glue is made out of software too, you still need that body of expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the software engineers, I have a dose of reality for you too: in my experience, businesses started by engineers sometimes suffer the opposite problem - they are technically interesting, but not worth paying for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amount of engineering time being spent &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_programming_languages&#34;&gt;creating new programming languages&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comparison_of_JavaScript_frameworks&#34;&gt;writing new javascript frameworks&lt;/a&gt; is astonishing. Building something with a different developer experience but no user-facing impact means you don&amp;rsquo;t have anything to sell. You&amp;rsquo;ve improved the ecosystem but haven&amp;rsquo;t actually put food on the table. And indeed, many of these creators, despite the value they&amp;rsquo;ve provided, are still living off of Patreon or Kickstarter. And while it might work for some, others are still &lt;a href=&#34;https://theoutline.com/post/2571/no-one-makes-a-living-on-patreon&#34;&gt;struggling&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t just need a circle of competence in software, but one in the area that you are trying to innovate in. If you&amp;rsquo;re making software that creates bingo cards, you have to understand that your users often search for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kalzumeus.com/2006/07/29/on-page-seo-for-small-companies/&#34;&gt;dolch sight words&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;a href=&#34;https://dilbertblog.typepad.com/the_dilbert_blog/2007/07/career-advice.html&#34;&gt;combination of the two areas&lt;/a&gt; that actually make your product rare and valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;find-the-time&#34;&gt;Find the time.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people look at me in wonder when I describe building a product while working a full time job. Don&amp;rsquo;t you already have too much to do? Do you not have a personal life?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul Graham goes as far as to suggest that working on other things would &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.paulgraham.com/die.html?&#34;&gt;lead to your startup&amp;rsquo;s death&lt;/a&gt;. It has now become quite common for people to leave high paying jobs to start companies, but often they don&amp;rsquo;t really know what company they&amp;rsquo;re starting, or why. Starting a company has become a kind of personal exploration in which, at the end of it, even if the startup doesn&amp;rsquo;t succeed, it&amp;rsquo;s okay. The specifics of what you learn are never very clear, but people seem to be pretty happy doing it, so I hesitate to criticize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, I think the approach is flawed. Many of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2019/02/and-then-there-was-thefacebookcom/582004/&#34;&gt;best&lt;/a&gt; companies were started as side projects, and that was before all of the swanky libraries and deployment infrastructure that is in common use today. I think the startup world is under the impression that you can only build something productively if you&amp;rsquo;re working 60 hours a week on it. Why 60? Why not 30? Why not 10? Isn&amp;rsquo;t one 60 hour week just a month and a half of 10 hour weeks? More importantly, can we build something in 10 hours today that would have taken 60 before?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect that while startups can move faster, at least in calendar time, working all day every day, they actually move far less &lt;em&gt;efficiently&lt;/em&gt;. That is, little old me on a 10 year old Macbook pro, working &lt;em&gt;solely in the hour before breakfast on weekdays&lt;/em&gt;, can simply outlast a sprinting rockstar programmer working for 100 hour weeks on ramen and coffee. That&amp;rsquo;s the real benefit - the rockstar programmer is dependent on finding someone to invest in him or her, has to find product market fit within a short amount of time, has to figure out hiring and legal and incorporation, etc. Because it&amp;rsquo;s just me, I only have to do the first one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classic software entrepreneurs are busy trying to &amp;ldquo;build a plane while flying it&amp;rdquo;. And as glorifying as that might seem, the plane you build is probably worse than it should be. Meanwhile, I&amp;rsquo;m happily tinkering on my own plane, and I have infinite runway because my day job pays all of my expenses and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prove your grit as an entrepreneur by starting your company while you&amp;rsquo;re working. Find the time. Depending on who you are, that could be late at night, early in the morning, during lunch, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;maximum-power-in-minimal-lines-of-code&#34;&gt;Maximum power in minimal lines of code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main value in being a solo entrepreneur is that you don&amp;rsquo;t have any of the overhead that happens at larger companies. The main downside? You don&amp;rsquo;t have any of their &lt;em&gt;resources&lt;/em&gt; either. Large companies like Google have amazing stuff they never release to the public, so writing code there is always going to be so much more joyful than writing it on your own. You get a sweet developer environment, can provision boxes on your own, and there are massive departments dedicated to looking after you. Of course you have the catering people, but also the operations people, the tools people, the product people, the design people, etc. Even if all those folks are dunderheads (which they aren&amp;rsquo;t) you&amp;rsquo;re not going to be able to replicate it solo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re fabricating steel beams over there, and it&amp;rsquo;s frankly far beyond your capacity. Don&amp;rsquo;t try, or you&amp;rsquo;ll get stuck TIG welding a corner piece. You&amp;rsquo;re building out of papier maché. It&amp;rsquo;s cheap, it&amp;rsquo;s soft, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to adjust. No, it probably won&amp;rsquo;t scale - but if you have too many users, you&amp;rsquo;ll figure out how to deal with that problem (and it&amp;rsquo;s hard even with steel beams).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your main weakness is you only have 5 hours a week on this project, and Google has, effectively, millions. But your strength is that you can do things that Google can&amp;rsquo;t. Remember those open-source lego blocks that were in the wild? You can use those in a way that Google never could, because they fully meet your needs and then some, whereas virtually &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; in the open source world (including Google&amp;rsquo;s own open source contributions) aren&amp;rsquo;t good enough within their ecosystem. At least, not by themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So your job isn&amp;rsquo;t to reinvent the wheel better than they can. It&amp;rsquo;s to cobble together a few spare parts, and see if your little local entropy reduction is worth more than it cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;build-vs-buy-always-buy&#34;&gt;Build vs Buy? Always Buy.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This kind of goes with the last one, but I&amp;rsquo;ll say it more explicitly. You should be spending your &lt;a href=&#34;https://mcfunley.com/choose-boring-technology&#34;&gt;innovation tokens&lt;/a&gt; as carefully as possible when starting your own project. And those tokens &lt;em&gt;probably&lt;/em&gt; should be spent on the things the user cares the most about, and not the other stuff (i.e. the user does not care about your dry cleaning).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few things in the dry cleaning category (which you should almost certainly buy, unless it&amp;rsquo;s the core competence of your business):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deployment infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Company email addresses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marketing emails&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Payment infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Databases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a fellar starting out with a business the size of a beta fish, this stuff should cost less than your weekly date night. Remember that much larger orgs are using this infrastructure too, so you can always tell yourself that &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; as a way of resting easy, and leave whatever special snowflake features you have in mind for your ideal system to your imagination instead of holding up your product development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cut-scope&#34;&gt;Cut scope&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software is an interesting thing, because you can change the problem more easily than you can change the solution. That means you can make life &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; hard for yourself by being too ambitious and wanting an app that not only solves the user&amp;rsquo;s problem, but also cooks their dinner, turns on the Al Green, and gives foot massages. &lt;strong&gt;Eliminate the excess&lt;/strong&gt;. The reason why is not because you don&amp;rsquo;t want to delight the user. You definitely do. But it&amp;rsquo;s better to have a pretty good solution to one problem than a half solution to 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practically speaking what this means is that you&amp;rsquo;ll build something that kinda works, and you&amp;rsquo;ll debate between doing some housekeeping that is absolutely necessary (completing your &lt;a href=&#34;https://stripe.com/&#34;&gt;payment infrastructure&lt;/a&gt;, for example) or adding feature Y. Always do the necessary stuff first. Then ship it. Most of the work is after you&amp;rsquo;ve built the product, after all, and your time is too limited to spend on features that aren&amp;rsquo;t absolutely necessary. Those 5 hours go by pretty quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Holding it all in your head</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/holding_in_your_head/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/holding_in_your_head/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Something I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed when working on larger programming projects is that my ability to add new code depends on what stage of the project I&amp;rsquo;m at. Early on, the code comes out fast. However, as time goes on and the project gets bigger, I find that it takes me up to an hour to &amp;ldquo;load the program into my head&amp;rdquo; before I can begin to add new features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good code is read most often by the writer, not by the computer. So if you keep your codebase concise and simple, you win twice: 1) it takes less time to read and understand and 2) it&amp;rsquo;s easier to modify. Perhaps that&amp;rsquo;s why experienced software engineers advise you to &lt;em&gt;pick a boring stack&lt;/em&gt;, particularly for projects you&amp;rsquo;re starting on your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly for me, the excitement of a new language or library often drives my initial interest in a project. It turns out this is stupid. Very soon afterward, I find myself blocked in an ever continual parade of stack overflow posts and difficult to comprehend bugs. For a while I thought I was &lt;em&gt;learning&lt;/em&gt; by going through this process. I usually wasn&amp;rsquo;t, because the new library did something I already knew how to do, just in a more fashionable way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does this principle apply to anything else? Yes, it does - it applies to pretty much all of my creative endeavors, including writing. If I try to write in a sophisticated, &amp;ldquo;wise&amp;rdquo; way, I find that it takes me a lot longer to load the dialogue into my head, improve it, and finalize it. The only reason this blog is beginning to gain momentum now is because I gave up on trying to write that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the scary thing. My writing is not just easier, it&amp;rsquo;s better than it was before. By using my natural voice and not coming off so stilted, I can approach topics and think more deeply through problems; I no longer have to think in a foreign language, so my focus is on the topic at hand rather than the words I&amp;rsquo;m using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, if you&amp;rsquo;ve been tracking the projects I&amp;rsquo;m working on, you should expect the number of interesting libraries I use to go &lt;strong&gt;down&lt;/strong&gt;. Sorry, the goal for me is a piece of software that accomplishes a goal, not source code that adheres most to the fashion of the day. And you can expect that I&amp;rsquo;ll be more productive as a consequence.&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human knowledge</title>
      <link>https://ssaraf.com/human_knowledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssaraf.com/human_knowledge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It took Newton the better part of 3 years to &amp;lsquo;invent&amp;rsquo; calculus. [1] He is considered to be one of the brightest mathematical minds to have ever lived. Yet most 17 year olds today are capable of mastering the same calculus he did. Why is that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s almost too obvious to say - it&amp;rsquo;s easier to learn something than it is to imagine it. More interestingly, there seems to be a kind of inflation with learning. The best high school students today might learn calculus at 15, rather than 17. And &amp;lsquo;best&amp;rsquo; in this instance actually seems to describe the school, rather than the student. It&amp;rsquo;s been well established that school quality is a far better predictor of academic success than anything else. [2]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&amp;rsquo;s not about how much horsepower your brain has. If subjects are taught to you in the right way, you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to master more difficult concepts than your parents did, at a younger age - both because of this inflation effect and because more will have been discovered by the time you get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anecdotally, there always seem to be folks who learn things far younger than others in their generation. For them, the general quality that sets them apart seems to be their precociousness, not their intelligence. Younger students often lack the discipline to focus for more advanced coursework. Once they gain the grit and work ethic of adults, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to stop them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus it&amp;rsquo;s always been a big frustration to me when people say &amp;ldquo;I just can&amp;rsquo;t do math&amp;rdquo;. Barring a diagnosable mental deficiency, this is never true. Most often students struggle not because the material is difficult but because they lack the discipline to keep working at it or are thinking about it from the wrong perspective. It is alarming how often it is the latter - kids work a lot harder than we give them credit for. But teachers are often abysmally bad at teaching them the right paradigms, often because they never learned them correctly in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common case I see of an incorrect paradigm is the student who leans on memorization to get through exams. Studies pretty clearly demonstrate that even with clever tricks like spaced repetition or mnemonics, long term recall for everyone is abysmally low. Relying on it to pass your test sounds good in the short term, but really it seems that you cut off the learning that other parts of your brain could be getting, like your reasoning skills. Perhaps that&amp;rsquo;s why absent minded professors have such bad memories. They don&amp;rsquo;t happen to have bad memories despite being able to reason well. They reason well &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; they have bad memories. They didn&amp;rsquo;t have the crutch to lean on, so their muscles grew stronger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some careers, like law or medicine, are so old fashioned they continue to teach as if memorizing lengthy material is necessary, even though practicing physicians and lawyers don&amp;rsquo;t remember the details from their licensing exams only a few years before. The paradigm they are really learning in medical school is a sense of what is &amp;ldquo;weirder than usual&amp;rdquo; and what isn&amp;rsquo;t. For symptoms that they don&amp;rsquo;t immediately recognize, they google it, like anyone else would. [3]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That isn&amp;rsquo;t to say that paradigms are everything. There will always be some basic facts and theories that need to be learned by rote in any field. One also may have to hone specific technical skills. But nonetheless it appears that every subject has some kind of limiting reagent - a few concepts that, once students really grok, make the rest of the field feel like a simple extension of what one already knows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The broader question is whether one can pick up new paradigms even beyond the young age at which most of them are initially acquired. I would argue that yes you can, so long as you already have the paradigm of paradigms - that ultimately the person who created the knowledge was not a young person. Newton was capable of inventing calculus at an older age. So you must be capable of at least understanding it now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t think you&amp;rsquo;re as smart as Newton was? Surely you&amp;rsquo;re not as dumb as an average 17 year old. Sandwiched between the two, there is virtually no concept across any subject of human knowledge that you are incapable of understanding. And your children will pick it up faster than you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average length of a PhD is about 7 years. [4] Even that is an overestimate of the knowledge one needs to acquire, since the majority of that time is spent trying to cobble together something to contribute to the field. That means the entire body of human knowledge, visualized as a swimming pool, is only 7 years deep. The average human lifespan is &amp;gt;78 years. [5]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only reason you aren&amp;rsquo;t an expert at something new is because you haven&amp;rsquo;t had the discipline and the paradigms needed to get there. I&amp;rsquo;m not offering a solution to this. But I do expect that within my lifetime, the vast human potential for knowledge acquisition and usage will not stay as untapped as it currently is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thanks&lt;/strong&gt; to Otis R and Karthik P for reading drafts and providing feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] The conflict between Newton and Leibniz is quite famous. But Fermat and other mathematicians discussed the principles of calculus long before both of them. In fact, Newton&amp;rsquo;s work is considered to be a new paradigm (along with a mathematical framework) on top of Fermat&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;theory of tangents&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/261805&#34;&gt;Card, &amp;ldquo;Does School Quality Matter&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] Good physicians don&amp;rsquo;t use wikipedia, but UptoDate and AccessMedicine are the medical equivalents, with proper citations. That said, you&amp;rsquo;d be frightened by how often wikipedia &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[4] The length of the average PhD appears to be decreasing in the past few years, which was quite surprising to me. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nsf.gov/statistics/2018/nsf18304/datatables/tab31.htm&#34;&gt;National Science Foundation, National Center for Science and Engineering Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[5] &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/gerontologist/article/55/6/901/2605490&#34;&gt;Crimmons, &amp;ldquo;Lifespan and Healthspan: Past, Present, and Promise&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>